Today’s Daf is צדיק ו Tzadik Vav 96, and we are in
the middle of a whole discussion here once again about כלים. Keilim.
Seems to be a recurring theme, and just to remind everybody what
we’re talking about, the Mishnah was discussing the issue about uprooting a
plant from a flower pot with a hole in it, it’s considered
connected to the ground and therefore it’s מלאכה; Melacha; without a hole
it’s not. And then the position of Rabbi Shimon that would always
consider something in a flower pot to not be connected. This led
the גמרא Gemara to discuss different types of sizes of holes
in flower pots that would change the status of what was in
it to being considered connected and not connected or to being considered
a vessel or not a vessel for various הלכות. Halachot.
So the last point the גמרא Gemara made, I guess maybe let's
read that a little bit from צדיק ה עמוד ב Tzadik Heh
Amud Bet just so we understand at least the minimum context. So
אמר רב אסי, Amar Rav Asi, the four lines from the bottom
on צדיק ה עמוד ב, Tzadik Heh Amud Bet, said Rav Asi,
שמעתי, shamati, I heard כלי חרס שיעורו כמוציא
רימון, Klei Cheres shiuro kemotze rimon, that the significant size for a
pottery vessel is for a pomegranate to fall out of it. That
was the largest size mentioned before. That’s quite unusual, normally once it
has a size in it the hole of a olive, it’s considered
no longer a vessel. The only exception would be if afterwards you
designated it and said I want to use this for like pomegranate.
Then it needs a hole the size of a pomegranate. So for
here he says that a blanket thing, it needs a hole the
size of a pomegranate. So for what purpose? So אמר ליה רבא,
Amar Lei Rava, so Rava said to him, שמא לא שמעת אלא
במוקף צמיד פתיל. shema lo shamata ela bemukaf tzamit patil. Maybe you
only heard it in a case where it’s surrounded with like a
sealed cover and that’s when that hole matters. What does that mean?
Because the Torah says that if you have a כלי חרס, klei
cheres, a pottery vessel in a room, in a house in which
there’s a dead body, so the טומאה tumah spreads throughout the room
and it goes into the pottery vessel. Pottery vessels become טמא tamei
through their opening, like through their inner side, not from the outside.
But if that opening is covered with a צמיד פתיל, tzamit patil,
with a tight cover, then the טומאה tumah cannot get in. Now
let's say the covering is covered with a tight cover but there’s
a hole on the side. Can the טומאה tumah get in through
some crack on the side? So רש"י, Rashi, I'll tell you what
תוספות Tosafot says in a minute, רש"י Rashi says no, actually the
טומאה tumah can only get in through the opening, not through some
crack on the side. But if it’s a big enough hole on
the side, so then it stops being considered a vessel altogether. And
once it stops being considered a vessel altogether, it doesn't have the
special הלכה halacha that it protects what's inside of it. Oh, because
I don't think I mentioned, when you have that sealed cover, not
only is the vessel טהור, tahor, but anything in that vessel is
also טהור, tahor, does not become טמא. tamei. So if you have
food in that vessel and it's covered with this tight seal, the
food does not become טמא tamei with the impurity of the dead
body. But if the hole is big enough on the side, even
if the opening is sealed, it stops being a vessel, it loses
that special הלכה halacha and the food becomes טמא. tamei. So how
big of a hole makes it stop being a vessel even when
it's covered with a צמיד פתיל, tzamit patil, a hole on the
side? So that would be a huge hole, מוציא רימון. motzi rimon.
But anything less than that, even if it’s enough of a vessel,
loses a vessel status that it will for example not become טמא
tamei itself, it still would be enough of a vessel to protect
the food inside it. It has to completely lose that status so
it no longer protects the food inside of it. And that is
the size of a מוציא רימון. motzi rimon. So the גמרא Gemara
says one minute, והא רבא הוא דאמר, Veha Rava Hu De'amar, didn't
Rava himself say
מוקף צמיד פתיל עד שיפחת רובו, mukaf tzamit patil ad sheyipachet rubo,
that a vessel surrounded with a צמיד פתיל tzamit patil it only
loses its status of a pottery vessel to protect what's inside only
if the majority is opened up, not מוציא רימון, motzi rimon, not
the size of a pomegranate, but only the majority? So how do
you reconcile these two statements? Is it the size of a pomegranate
or the majority? So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא, lo kashya,
it's not difficult, הא ברברבי הא בזוטרי. Ha Beravrevi Ha Bezutri. Depends
if it's big or if it’s small. Now which way does that
go? So if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says ברברבי,
beravrevi, if it's big, then ברובו, berubo, then you need the majority
of it to be, because then if you only had the size
of a pomegranate it might be not substantial if it’s a huge
vessel. But if it’s a small one then the size of a
pomegranate is enough. Now תוספות Tosafot says the obvious question. תוספות Tosafot
says, I mean you could understand the logic of that, the bigger
it is the bigger hole you need, right? A hole the size
of a pomegranate wouldn't be significant if it’s a huge vessel. But
look at תוספות, Tosafot, he says פירש בקונטרס רברבי ברובו זוטרי כמוציא
רימון וקשיא ליה דאין זה שיעור
ומקרי רברבי ומקרי זוטרי לידע איזו כמוציא רימון. Peirash Bekontras, Ravrevi Berubo,
Zutri Kemotzi Rimon. Vekasha Lei Di'ein Zeh Shiur, Umakari Ravrevi Umakari Zutri
Leda Eizu Kemotzi Rimon. What do you mean bigger or smaller? How
big? How small? Right? I mean, okay, logically you understand but you
have to make some type of a quantifiable difference so we can
actually apply the הלכה. halacha. So תוספות Tosafot actually says it's the
reverse. If it is small, then רוב rov is enough because if
it’s small, let’s say it’s only this. then if you say you
needed a hole the size of a pomegranate, that would be 80%
of the vessel. So if it's small, if the size of a
pomegranate is bigger than the majority, then you only need the majority
for it to lose its status of a vessel. In a large
vessel where the size where the size of the pomegranate is smaller
than the majority of it, then you only need the size of
a pomegranate. So basically it's another way of saying a hole that's
the majority or a hole the size of the pomegranate whichever is
smaller. And as soon as you get to the smaller of those
two, then it loses its status of a vessel. Okay, so that
is this issue about saving with a צמיד פתיל. tzamid patil. Now,
before we move on to the next discussion about pottery vessels I
should mention there's this big תוספות Tosafot here ולענין צמיד פתיל ul'inyan
tzamid patil because תוספות Tosafot is very bothered that there are other
גמרות gemarot that make it sound like if a vessel has a
hole on the side, the טומאה tumah can get in on the
side even if it's not a huge gaping hole that makes it
stop being a vessel. So which way is it? So one explanation
of תוספות Tosafot is all those גמרות gemarot are talking when the
hole on the side is made as a hole for the vessel.
Like it's not that the vessel is broken, but it's made to
serve as a type of a hole. But if it really is
broken on the side, mean like a spout? Yeah, something like a
spout, I guess. But if it really is broken on the side,
then רש״י Rashi is right, טומאה tumah would not get in through
a crack. טומאה tumah only gets in through an official opening. Okay,
he has a couple of other explanations as well, but I wanted
you to be aware that it's not so clear
that
טומאה tumah can't get in through a hole on the side, that's
how רש״י Rashi reads it, there's a whole discussion in תוספות Tosafot
exactly what are the parameters of that. But assuming it can't, then
it's until the whole thing fully loses its status of a vessel
and that's this huge hole. Okay now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר
רב אסי, Amar Rav Assi, שונים, shonim, we teach, כלי חרס שיעורו
בכונס משקה. kli cheres shiuro b'koneis mashke.
The normal way in which a vessel can lose its status for
like טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah is if it has a hole the
size that liquid can come in. Okay, if you remember the גמרא
Gemara said before once it's that size, for example, you can't use
it for a vessel for
like מי
חטאת, mei chatat, but okay, so that's like a minimum size normally.
In other cases it would go by it would go by the
size of an olive. But ולא אמרו מוציא משקה, v'lo amru motzi
mashke, the only time they said that even if liquid came out,
it was enough to be a problem, right if you understand the
way like the pressure works, if it's filled with liquid and then
you have a tiny hole because the gravity whatever is pushing down
on the liquid, a small hole the liquid will come out. Whereas
if you put it into liquid and you want the liquid to
go into the vessel, you need the hole to be bigger. Okay,
so מוציא משקה motzi mashke is a smaller hole than כונס משקה.
koneis mashke. Is that clear how that works? Okay, so the normal
size that starts mattering by a pottery vessel is כונס משקה, koneis
mashke, only if liquid big enough that liquid can come in. What
is the one case that מוציא משקה motzi mashke significant? Smaller even
if it's so small that liquid will go out even if it
won't go in? אלא לענין גיסטרא בלבד, ela l'inyan gistera bilvad, only
regarding a pottery shard. If you have a pottery shard, a broken
piece of pottery that you have decided, you know what, I'm still
going to use this as a vessel, it's true it's broken but
there's enough here to use and I'll still use it as a
vessel, there because it's only barely a vessel for purposes of טומאה
וטהרה tumah v'taharah and other purposes, then even the smallest hole will
make it lose its status. And now the- it was yesterday. It's
reframing it and now the גמרא Gemara says why. מאי טעמא? Mai
taama? What's the reason for this? אמר מר זוטרא בריה דרב נחמן,
Amar Mar Zutra breih d'Rav Nachman, לפי שאין אומרים הוי גיסטרא לגיסטרא
lefi she'ein omrim havei gistera l'gistera because you don't say let's bring
a patch for the patch. Okay, right isn't there wasn't there a
phrase like poor person somebody so poor he has his patches have
patches? Right, so here so here you wouldn't do that. I mean
so therefore once it gets even a small hole, that's it, the
whole thing was barely a vessel to begin with you'd throw it
out. But if you had a normal vessel, a good vessel that
had a tiny hole, maybe you would patch it up and therefore
it's only a problem when the hole gets to be or only
changes the status when the hole gets to be a little bit
bigger. Okay. אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, פליגי בה תרי אמוראי במערבא. pligi
bah try amora'i b'ma'arava. There's a debate of two אמוראים Amoraim in
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. רבי יוסי ברבי אבין
ורבי יוסי
בר זבדא. Rabbi Yose barbi Avin v'Rabbi Yose bar Zavda. It's quite
interesting actually I just want to mention, I didn't check how many
times this happens, but this is a often we have the two
רבי יוסי'ס Rabbi Yose's introduced from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael with this:
פליגי בה תרי אמוראי במערבא pligi bah try amora'i b'ma'arava and these
two רבי יוסי'ס Rabbi Yose's and they don't know which one said
which. So this actually happens a few times in the בבלי Bavli
this exact thing that the two רבי יוסי'ס Rabbi Yose's in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael debated this and here's what they said they don't
know which one said which. Okay so what did they say? חד
אמר כמוציא רימון chad amar k'motzi rimon וחד אמר כשורש קטן. v'chad
amar k'shoresh katan. One said that the hole that's significant is the
size of a pomegranate, which is the biggest size we said, and
the other said that the hole that's significant is the size of
a small little root which isn't the very smallest size, but it's
certainly smaller than for example the size of an olive. It's not
so they pretty much went to extreme opposites. and the way to
remember that they took the extreme positions about this and not a
middle position is וסימנך v'simancha and the way to remember that they
took the extreme positions about this and not a middle position is
אחד אמר הרבה ואחד אמר הממעט ובלבד שיכוון לבו לשמים. echad amar
marbeh ve'echad amar hamamat uvilvad sheyachaven libo lashamayim.
Whether you do a lot or whether you do a little, as
long as you have the right כוונה, kavanah, right, which is what
the גמרא Gemara says about bringing קרבנות korbanot or we say about
דאבנינג. davening. So to tell you the idea of that's a little
mnemonic to remember one of them took the most extreme position, the
מרבה, marbeh, the other took the ממעט, mamat, they all were לשם
שמים. leshem shamayim. No, but anyway, now, what are they arguing about?
A hole for what purpose? We discussed a lot of different points
about what the hole matters. So if you take a look רש"י
Rashi says, פליגי בהכשר זרעים pligi be-hechsher zera'im regarding this issue about
when are the seeds in it considered to be in the ground
and can no longer become טמא. tamei. תוספות Tosafot says no. תוספות
Tosafot says פליגי בתרי אמוראי, pligi bitrei amora'i, if you look at
the first wide line, פירש בקונטרס דלענין הכשר זרעים פליגי. peireish bakuntres
dile'inyan hechsher zera'im pligi. ואומר רבנו תם דבמסכת עוקצין תנן הכשר זרעים
כשורש קטן. ve'omer Rabbeinu Tam debemasechet Uktzin tnan hechsher zera'im keshoresh katan.
No,
it's clear in עוקצין Uktzin that we go by the size of
the root. אלא אמר רבנו תם לענין מוקף צמיד פתיל פליגי ela
amar Rabbeinu Tam le'inyan mukaf tzamid patil pligi what we were just
discussing. How big of a hole that even if it's covered with
a tight cover, right, what size hole will it now stop being
a vessel so the טומאה tumah can get in? So one position
is the רמון, rimon, the pomegranate, which is what we were saying,
that when it's covered with a tight cover it needs to be
a huge hole to stop being a vessel, and the other said
even a smaller one. You understand of course why רש"י Rashi said
that it was about הכשר זרעים hechsher zera'im and not צמיד פתיל,
tzamid patil, because שורש קטן shoresh katan suggests we're talking about something
agricultural, so it either could be זרעים, zera'im, seeds, or it could
be the question of let's say תולש, toleish, which we started in
our משנה, mishnah, okay, picking the leaves off something growing in a
flower plant, plant. But anyway תוספות Tosafot says no maybe that's even
a possible size for other things and we're still talking about צמיד
פתיל. tzamid patil. Okay. אמר רבי חנינא בר כהנא משמיה דרבי אליעזר,
amar Rabbi Chanina bar Kahana mishmei deRabbi Eliezer, כלי חרס שיעורו כמוציא
זיתים. klei cheres shi'uro kemotzi zeitim. A pottery vessel you go by
the size of olives. Now again, for what purpose? So רש"י Rashi
says this is the normal purpose of losing the status of a
vessel so it stops becoming טמא, tamei, right, and that's what we
said before, the normal size hole for a pottery vessel that it
loses its status as a vessel is an olive, is a hole
the size of an olive. So that's restating what we said yesterday.
And once it's that way it cannot become טמא tamei anymore. ומר
קשישא בריה דרבא מסיים בה משמיה דרבי אליעזר. u-Mar Kashisha brei de-Rava
mesayem bah mishmei de-Rabbi Eliezer. But מר קשישא Mar Kashisha the son
of רבא Rava ended it in the name of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, the first name was in the name of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, he added a final comment of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, והרי
הן ככלי גללים וככלי אבנים וככלי אדמה. ve-harei hen ke-chlei glalim u-ke-chlei
avanim u-ke-chlei adamah. They are like vessels made out of, and here
you see that it's clear we're talking about טומאה tumah because of
the comparison, they're made out of vessels made out of like a
dry dung or out of stone or out of earth, meaning not
pottery, but earth. What are the status of those vessels?
שאין מקבלין טומאה לא מדברי תורה ולא מדברי סופרים. she'ein mekabelin tumah
lo midivrei Torah velo midivrei sofrim. Those vessels are completely out of
the category of טומאה, tumah, they cannot become טמא tamei not biblically,
not rabbinically. So once a pottery vessel has a hole in it
the size of an olive, it has no טומאה tumah not biblical,
not rabbinical, it's completely stops being a vessel. ולענין צמיד פתיל, u-le'inyan
tzamid patil, but just in case you forgot what we were discussing
before this, that's for טומאה וטהרה tumah ve-taharah for it to become
טמא, tamei, but regarding stopping to protect the things inside of it
if it's got a tight seal, that's עד שיפחת רובו, ad sheyipachat
rubo, that goes back to the idea of the majority. So for
losing this protection of the things inside of it if it's in
the same room as a dead body, we've had the idea of
majority, the idea of a pomegranate, and maybe another size depending on
how you read the earlier גמרא. Gemara. But for it to become
טמא tamei or טהור, tahor, there it was enough to lose its
status of a vessel and no longer becomes טמא tamei the size
of an olive, and then it's completely out of the category. תוספות
Tosafot points out the emphasis, why do you have to make such
a huge statement, it's like a stone vessel completely out of the
category? Because yesterday we said that if it had a hole the
size of an olive and you designated it for pomegranate, it would
still become טמא tamei until it had a bigger hole. So תוספות
Tosafot understands the point of this statement is no I'm sorry, once
it has a hole the size of an olive, I don't care
what you designated it for, for טומאה tumah purposes it completely stops
being a vessel even if you've designated it for other use. Okay,
and with that we end this discussion, הדרן עלך המצניע hadran alach
Ha-Matzni'a of, of vessels. Now again, as I keep on telling you,
the interesting thing about
שבת Shabbat is the recurrence of certain themes. So טומאה וטהרה tumah
ve-taharah of vessels is certainly a recurring theme, but more and we
just spent today on that, but more than טומאה וטהרה tumah ve-taharah
of vessels, the recurring theme, you might even say the dominant theme,
is that of carrying. So we actually thought we were finally transitioning
out of carrying because just to remind us the importance of the
last משניות mishnayot we just read, the last משניות mishnayot talk about
principles starting with carrying but moving on to other things which are
core principles across all the מלאכות. melachot. So we talked about carrying
like with the back of your hand, with your leg, in front
of you it moved behind you, that's the principle of כלאחר יד
ke-le'achar yad or שינוי. shinui. That that's an exemption. Then the משנה
mishna talked about הוציאו שנים. hotzio'u shnayim.
If two people do a מלאכה melacha and both each one is
able to do it by himself. Okay, that then they're exempt, if
you needed both to do it, then they'd be חייב, chayav, but
that's the principle of שנים שעשו, shnayim she'asu, two people who did
it. And then it discussed זה יכול וזה אינו יכול ze yachol
ve-ze eino yachol and how that would play out. Then you got
from that to the discussion in the גמרא Gemara about, what do
you call it, about no, in the next משנה mishna about what
happens if you carry a live person out and because of the
principle that חי נושא את עצמו chai nosei et atzmo can exempt
you. Okay, now that is specific to הוצאה, hotza'ah, obviously you don't
have חי נושא את עצמו chai nosei et atzmo in other things.
But again, it's a fascinating principle, and that might be similar to
the idea of שנים שעשו, shnayim she'asu, right? Why does חי נושא
את עצמו chai nosei et atzmo make a difference? If I carry
out a 200-pound person, I'm פטור patur because he's helping his own
weight. If I carry out a little bit of food the size
of a pressed date, I'm חייב. chayav. So תוספות Tosafot asks that
question and תוספות Tosafot says, yeah, it's clearly not because it weighs
less. So maybe תוספות Tosafot says it's a type of שנים שעשו,
shnayim she'asu, right? I'm carrying him out and he's carrying himself out.
So it's a type of שנים שעשו. shnayim she'asu. But תוספות Tosafot
says no, but then I'm the real one doing it, he's just
the מסייע, mesayei'a, and we said מסייע, mesayei'a, right, מסייע אין בו
ממש. mesayei'a ein bo mamash. So it can't be based on that.
So תוספות Tosafot says it must be like just one of these
things that it's not the way it was in the משכן. Mishkan.
That, you know, in the משכן Mishkan they carried dead weight as
opposed to a live person. This becomes very important, what the parameters
of that are about issues around carrying a baby and is it
דרבנן. de-rabbanan. I'm not, okay, just reviewing, we can talk about the
הלכה halacha later. Okay, and how you know, and what if the
baby can't walk by himself, תוספות Tosafot discusses whether or not that
matters. Okay, but that was a principle about carrying oneself. We also
had the whole idea about a minimum with a כלי, kli, less
than the minimum in a כלי, kli, is the כלי kli negated
to the minimum? Okay, and then we said, I'm just reviewing some
of the stuff at the end because again, this reminds us of
the non-הוצאה hotza'ah aspects we spoke about. We talked about, you know,
fingernails and cutting your fingernails. So again, that started with an issue
of שינוי. shinuy. You cut with your own, you know, your hand,
not with a כלי. kli. Sometimes you need to use a כלי
kli to make it considered normal or type of a מלאכה melacha
and not with your own fingernails. But it also led to questions
about
what do you call it, about other types of things about the
body, about putting on makeup and braiding your hair. Can those things
really be מלאכות? melachot? רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer seemed to have a
very broader definition of מלאכה. melacha. He called things like braiding your
hair מלאכה, melacha, putting on the makeup or whatever, various types of
things מלאכה, melacha, whereas the rabbis said, no, no, it's only דרבנן.
de-rabbanan. And that's interesting. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer in general seems to
have a slightly different approach to מלאכות melachot on שבת. Shabbat. Led
to a whole discussion about milking, and is milking a מלאכה, melacha,
making cheese, and what type of a מלאכה melacha is that, and
so on. And then we came back to this idea about what's
considered connected to the ground. Again, and that again, by the way,
and I shouldn't say came back, and that again is a type
of a question of שינוי, shinuy, or if not שינוי, shinuy, defining
the exact parameters of other מלאכות. melachot. So we've discussed שינוי, shinuy,
we've discussed שנים שעשו, shnayim she'asu, we discussed fingernails, right? And is
that a מלאכה? melacha? Is that maybe a שינוי shinuy or not
a שינוי shinuy or is that well enough done? If it's done
in a certain way, sloppy way, is that enough to constitute a
מלאכה melacha or not? The גמרא Gemara discussed things like milking and
making cheese. We're dealing with other מלאכות. melachot. Then we discussed this
מלאכה melacha of תולש, toleish, and תולש toleish requires connected to the
ground. What's defined as connected to the ground if it's in a
flowerpot? Okay,
so all these things, we seem like finally we're getting into the
discussion of defining parameters of other מלאכות melachot or defining some universal
principles like שינוי shinuy or not. Anyway, we turn back in this
פרק perek to a full פרק perek devoted again to carrying. Okay?
So, but we will after this finally get to all the other
מלאכות. melachot. So it was like a little bit of a tease,
but let's not forget that we had some really important principles about
מלאכות melachot in general criteria, and we will now go back to
carrying for one more פרק. perek. Yes.
At first we were surprised about the idea that it's somewhat arbitrary
and somewhat counterintuitive. We could carry a piece of furniture all the
way to Yonkers, but we can't carry a key across Broadway.
You mean because of issues about what defines רשות reshut or not.
Yeah. Right, so but that's the question. I mean, do you just
say, okay, yeah, that's just the הלכה, halacha, which is essentially what
תוספות Tosafot says. Yeah, fine, the הלכה halacha is dead weight. Right,
but you have to say that rather than trying to fit the
exclusion into some other category, you have to make the exclusion an
independent category. Okay. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara continues with
a new פרק perek back to the major theme of carrying. Let's
take a look. המוציא מרשות היחיד לרשות הרבים ומרשות הרבים לרשות היחיד.
Ha-motzi me-reshut ha-yachid li-reshut ha-rabbim u-me-reshut ha-rabbim li-reshut ha-yachid.
Now, not just carrying, but even if you throw. You throw something
from a רשות היחיד, reshut ha-yachid, which is
which is
private domain but here we know means
surrounded
by four walls, or three walls, whatever, into a public domain, a
major thoroughfare, or from רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim to רשות היחיד, reshut
ha-yachid, חייב chayav you've transgressed because even though you didn't carry even
though you threw it doesn't matter. That's point number one. מרשות היחיד
לרשות היחיד רשות הרבים באמצע. me-reshut ha-yachid l'reshut ha-yachid reshut ha-rabim be-emtza.
How about you threw from one house to the next house across
the street? You threw out of your window into your neighbor's window
across the street and there was a רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim there
was the street was in the middle a major thoroughfare. So רבי
עקיבא מחייב וחכמים פוטרין. Rabbi Akiva mechayev ve-chachamim potrin. רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says you're חייב chayav
and the rabbis say you're exempt. Didn't we have this? Yes we
did well it was quoted before I mean the גמרא Gemara does
quote things in other places. So למימרא? le-meimra?
You mean above ten טפחים tefachim or not? Excellent question. So two
ways of reading why רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you're חייב. chayav.
One is you threw under ten טפחים tefachim which as we know
is the air space of רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim and therefore it
passed through the air space it's like it came to rest okay
and that is the principle of קלוטה כמאן שהונחה דמי keluta ke-man
she-huncha dami way in the beginning of the מסכת masechet when it
got absorbed caught in the air space it's like it actually was
placed down and if that's true it could even be that you're
חייב chayav twice from house A into the street and from the
street into house B okay that passing through the air space is
like coming to rest. That's one way of understanding רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. We will let's read the end of the משנה mishna and
we'll see another way of understanding רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. כיצד? keitzad?
And now when the חכמים chachamim say you're exempt from house A
to house B it's not all the time. When is this true?
How is this true? שתי גזוזטראות shtei gezuztraot if you have two
balconies זו כנגד זו zo keneged zo one facing another like on
two opposite sides of the street like we just discussed and the
balcony is a רשות היחיד reshut ha-yachid okay because let's say it's
got a fence around like a wall around it okay so you
have two balconies facing one another on opposite sides of the street
זו כנגד זו ברשות הרבים zo keneged zo be-reshut ha-rabim
with one opposite the other on you know with a public domain
between them המושיט והזורק מזו לזו פטור ha-moshit ve-ha-zorek mi-zu le-zu patur
whether you throw from house A to house B or you hand
over something from house A to house B you're exempt like we
said before from one רשות היחיד reshut ha-yachid to another with a
רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim in the middle you're exempt. But here's a
case where you actually are חייב. chayav. היו שתיהם בגזוזטרא אחת hayu
sheteihem be-gezuztra achat
let's say they were both on the same side of a street
and there was a רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim between them how does
that work it means if this thing like this גמרא Gemara is
the street the street is going lengthwise right so the normal case
is I have a house here and a house here okay but
let's say I have two houses here now if I normally pass
from a window from a house on one side of the street
to a neighboring house on the same side of the street I
would be going it would be going over our yards it wouldn't
be going over the street right because our but if you have
a balcony that overhangs the street and your balcony the other guy's
balcony overhangs the street when you pass from one balcony to the
next you're passing alongside the length of the street below you is
the actual street okay so rather than going across the street you're
passing over רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim with according to the with along
the length of רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim is that is that clear
okay so that makes all the difference and
you're above ten טפחים tefachim when you do that המושיט חייב והזורק
פטור ha-moshit chayav ve-ha-zorek patur
if you hand over from one balcony to the neighboring balcony on
the same side of street with a רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim underneath
you you're חייב chayav but if you throw you're exempt what is
all this about even though normally throwing is the same as carrying
and anyway why do you חייב chayav שכך הייתה עבודת הלוים she-kach
hayetah avodat ha-leviyim this was a special case that happened in the
משכן Mishkan that they would do something just like this by handing
over. What was the case? שתי עגלות זו אחר זו ברשות הרבים
shtei agalot zo achar zo be-reshut ha-rabim you had your whole you
know caravan so you had two two wagons side by side and
behind them were another two wagons side by side okay here's your
street right wagon A B C D right or you know or
A B A prime B prime anyway two wagons side by side
and you know then they would go by the length of רשות
הרבים. reshut ha-rabim. Now how would they what would they do? So
the משכן Mishkan was let's say here. Here's the משכן Mishkan okay
they didn't have paved roads there they where wherever they went that
was the road. So here's the משכן Mishkan they got to start
taking it apart in order to carry. So they line up the
wagons two right next to facing the משכן Mishkan and two in
front of them. So what are they going to do they take
apart the משכן Mishkan they hand the stuff here into this wagon
this guy in this wagon move it over hand hand over to
the next wagon the next that wagon fills up then this wagon
fills up same thing going on on this side all four wagons
are filled up then they can move forward. So what were they
doing here? They were passing from one wagon to the next if
the wagon was right you know had walls around it it was
raised from the street whatever it was a רשות היחיד reshut ha-yachid
so they went from a רשות reshut I don't know they went
from רשות היחיד reshut ha-yachid to רשות היחיד reshut ha-yachid with the
רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim under you know between them and they went
alongside the length of the רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim okay is that
pretty
clear?
So here's your street, it's time to take, right, here's your רשות
הרבים. Reshut HaRabbim. It's time to take a... I mean it's not
really a street where you're going to move as a רשות הרבים.
Reshut HaRabbim. That's the משכן. Mishkan. Here are all your boards. Right.
Time to dismantle it and move. Okay, so you get your wagons
to line up, right,
and here's wagon one, right, with whatever.
Right, you got your wagons lined up ready to go two by
two.
And what do they do? They put the boards onto this and
onto this, and from this one they move it over here, and
from this one they move it over here. Okay, so they're going
from רשות היחיד. Reshut HaYachid. These wagons are רשות היחיד, Reshut HaYachid,
right? They're four by four, they have let's say some, you know,
some walls around them. So from רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid to רשות
היחיד Reshut HaYachid with the רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabbim in the middle,
but it's alongside the length. So this is a חיוב chiyuv only
when you do exactly like this: רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid to רשות
היחיד Reshut HaYachid by handing. They didn't throw the beams. And when
they're along the length of the רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabbim, not when
they're on opposite sides of the רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabbim. And they
never did the other way around. Now what you really wonder is
why didn't they just load these up and then go?
Move these forward? I don't
know.
Okay, I have no idea why the משנה Mishnah assumes that this
is what they did, but I know. Okay, so anyway, שהיו זו
אחר זו ברשות הרבים מושיטין הקרשים מזו לזו, Shehayu zo achar zo
bireshut harabim moshitin hakrashim mizo lizo,
they would hand the beams from the back ones to the front
ones. So it would be רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid to רשות היחיד
Reshut HaYachid along the length of
רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabbim, אבל לא זורקין, aval lo zorkin, they would
never throw it. So this is, this once again shows you the
arbitrary nature of הוצאה, hotza'ah, right? We keep on talking about how
הוצאה hotza'ah is very much focused on the process, not on the
result, because there isn't a result. Why we have to learn every
single different part of the process directly, which is actually going to
be the rest of the גמרא Gemara today, as opposed to normally
we can have a principle of an אב av and then we
just can figure it out. Oh, you can't do baking, can't do
cooking, can't do frying, can't do this, can't do that. Here we
have to learn every single one because it's all about the exact
process. And here you have a great example of it, that any
slight deviation from this process, from this exact way, you're פטור. patur.
If it's across רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabbim rather than alongside, you're exempt.
If you throw rather than hand, you're exempt. You're only חייב chayav
in this exact scenario. And that again shows you the arbitrary nature
of הוצאה hotza'ah and of the focus on a particular type of
a process. Now, I want to say one more thing about רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva before we turn the page, going back to David's
point, which is that why does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva say you're
חייב chayav when you throw from רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid to רשות
היחיד Reshut HaYachid with a רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabbim in the middle?
He might have a broader definition of what you can learn out
from this case. Meaning it might not be because it's under ten
טפחים tefachim and it's like it came to rest in רשות הרבים.
Reshut HaRabbim. He might be saying, oh, from this case I'll learn
any case of רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid to another רשות היחיד Reshut
HaYachid with a רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabbim in the middle, even if
you throw it, even if it's higher than ten טפחים. tefachim. Okay,
so that might be what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is based on.
He might have a broader definition of what constitutes this case.
He's more willing to abstract.
He's more willing to abstract, maybe. The גמרא Gemara will have two
different reads of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. But for the חכמים, Chachamim,
it is only exactly this way: alongside the length of רשות הרבים,
Reshut HaRabbim, same side of the street, okay, handing, not throwing, and
this is this special case of חיוב. chiyuv. Let's take a look
now at the גמרא. Gemara. רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid to רשות היחיד?
Reshut HaYachid?
No, they don't agree to חייב chayav there. Okay, so we're going
to ask that in the גמרא. Gemara. So now that we've just
implicitly made the point that you have to really know the, you
know, that every single מלאכה melacha you can't abstract, I mean every
single part of carrying you can't abstract, we're now going to have
to figure out how we know all the different aspects of carrying.
So let's take a look. What the גמרא Gemara says. מכדי, Michdi,
says the גמרא, Gemara, let's see. זריקה תולדה דהוצאה היא. Zrika toldah
dehotza'ah hee.
זריקה Zrika is a תולדה, toldah, is a derivative of the general
parent of carrying. הוצאה גופא היכא כתיבא? Hotza'ah gufa heicha ktiva?
Where was הוצאה hotza'ah ever written? So how do we know that
הוצאה hotza'ah is an אב? av? First let's talk about הוצאה, hotza'ah,
then we'll worry about all the other things. Let's talk about classic
הוצאה. hotza'ah. What's classic הוצאה? hotza'ah? You're not throwing it, you're holding
it, and you're carrying it from, you're מוציא motzi going out, you're
carrying it from private to public. How do we know that basic
principle? Now, look at תוספות Tosafot before we see the answer. תוספות
Tosafot says, ואף על גב דהוה במשכן כדאמר הם הורידו קרשים מן
העגלה, Ve'af al gav dehava beMishkan k'd'amar hem horidu krashim min ha'agalah,
even though it was in the משכן, Mishkan, right? Where do any
of the מלאכות melachot written? We just learn it out from what
they did in the משכן. Mishkan. It says, מכל מקום אי לאו
דכתיב לא הוי מחייב עלה, Mikol makom ee lav d'ketiv lo havei
mechayev aleh, if it hadn't been written specifically by carrying you would
not be חייב. chayav. Why? לפי שמלאכה גרועה היא, Lefi shemelacha gerua
hee, because it is a lower מלאכה. melacha. Again, meaning what? It's
not a productive labor. So therefore everything else, once you say משכן,
Mishkan, we'll figure it out from here. Great, we got it, we'll
take it from here. But carrying, it's not a productive labor. So
therefore you need to learn it directly, and you're going to need
to learn the אב av directly and you're going to need to
learn the תולדות tolados directly. Everything has to be said explicitly because
you cannot abstract and it's not the same type thing as other
מלאכות. melachos. So let's go back to the גמרא Gemara and see
where we learn it from. אמר רב יוחנן דאמר קרא Amar Rav
Yochanan d'amar kra because the פסוק pasuk says ויצו משה ויעבירו קול
במחנה. Vayetzav Moshe vayaviru kol bamachaneh.
Moshe gave out the command and a, you know, an announcement was
made throughout the camp, right? Everybody stop bringing, we have enough stuff.
ויכלא העם מהביא. Vayikalei ha-am me-havi. Okay. והמלאכה הייתה דיים, V'hamelachah hayesah
dayam, it was sufficient. So משה היכן הוה יתיב? Moshe heichan hava
yasiv? Where was Moshe? במחנה לויה. B'Machaneh Leviyah.
He lived in מחנה לויה. Machaneh Leviyah. ומחנה לויה רשות הרבים הוי?
U'Machaneh Leviyah reshus ha-rabim hava? That was a רשות הרבים. reshus ha-rabim.
How do we know? We don't. רש"י Rashi says we assume that
if Moshe was there, everybody else was there as well. So maybe
it wasn't the רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim of the street, maybe it
was that other רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim of a public gathering square.
So the גמרא Gemara assumes that מחנה לויה Machaneh Leviyah was רשות
הרבים. reshus ha-rabim. So they were bringing it to Moshe, so they
were bringing it to a רשות
הרבים. reshus ha-rabim.
Okay. וקאמר להו לישראל v'ka-amar lehu l'Yisrael and he was telling them
לא תפיקו ותיתו מרשות היחיד דידכו לרשות הרבים. lo seifiku v'saisu me-reshus
ha-yachid didchu l'reshus ha-rabim.
Don't bring from your private domain, your homes, into the מחנה לויה,
Machaneh Leviyah, into רשות הרבים. reshus ha-rabim. So there you go, that's
הוצאה hotza'ah from a רשות היחיד reshus ha-yachid to a רשות הרבים.
reshus ha-rabim. So the גמרא Gemara says,
who knows all these things? Who knows? וממאי דבשבת קאי? u-mimai d'b'Shabbos
kai? Who told you that happened on שבת? Shabbos? דילמא בחול קאי?
dilma b'chol kai?
Maybe it was a weekday. ומשום דשלמה לה מלאכה? u-mishum d'shlimah lei
melachah? He wasn't saying, "Stop doing הוצאה!" hotza'ah! That wasn't what he
was saying. He was saying, "Stop bringing stuff, we don't need it,
we have enough stuff." Okay. How do you know to read this
as if he's telling them stop doing הוצאה? hotza'ah? Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says כדכתיב והמלאכה הייתה דיים, k'dichesiv v'hamelachah hayesah dayam, the
what they had produced was sufficient. No. גמר העברה העברה Gamar ha'avarah
ha'avarah מיום הכפורים. mi-Yom HaKippurim. We make a link because it says
ויעבירו, vayaviru, they passed, they made an announcement, from a similar word
by יום כפור. Yom Kippur. כתיב הכא ויעבירו קול במחנה, Kesiv hacha
vayaviru kol bamachaneh, they made an announcement throughout the camp, וכתיב התם
u-kesiv hasam it says there והעברת שופר תרועה, v'ha'avarta shofar teruah, you
shall blow the shofar blast throughout, you know, in all of your
dwelling places on יום כפור Yom Kippur of the יובל. Yovel. That's
specifically of the יובל. Yovel. מה להלן ביום אסור, Mah la-halan b'yom
assur, the same way there it says on the tenth of תשרי,
Tishrei, on the tenth of the seventh month, so it's on a
day forbidden in מלאכה, melachah, אף כאן ביום איסור. af kan b'yom
issur. Here too, when Moshe said it, ויעבירו, vayaviru, it was a
day forbidden on מלאכה, melachah, it was שבת, Shabbos, and he said
stop bringing, which we say means stop taking out from רשות היחיד
reshus ha-yachid to רשות הרבים. reshus ha-rabim. Yes, Charlie?
But there are things that are prohibited on יום כפור Yom Kippur
that aren't prohibited on שבת. Shabbos.
All right, what can I tell you? But the other question that
תוספות Tosafos says is who needs all of this?
If they did it before the process of the משכן, Mishkan, then
Moshe didn't have to tell them it was אסור. assur. All we
have to know is that they did this for the process of
the משכן Mishkan and the פסוק pasuk even implicitly calls it a
מלאכה. melachah. והמלאכה הייתה דיים. V'hamelachah hayesah dayam.
So who needs, one minute, so who needs to say that he
was telling them stop doing this on שבת? Shabbos? Just say we
see that carrying was called a מלאכה melachah and that's what they
did in the making of the משכן Mishkan and therefore we learn
that it's a מלאכה, melachah, right? Because we learn from what they
did in the משכן Mishkan during the rest of the week what
is defined as a מלאכה melachah on שבת. Shabbos. So why do
we have to say that they were doing it on שבת? Shabbos?
Say like everything else, like the cooking and the baking and the
building and all of that, they were doing it during the rest
of the week and from there we learn it's a מלאכה. melachah.
So תוספות Tosafos actually has a גרסא girsa of the גמרא Gemara
that cuts out the 15 lines or whatever that we just read
because exactly for that point, that there's no need to say that
it happened on שבת. Shabbos. But again, maybe because of the weakness
of this idea that carrying is a מלאכה, melachah, we want the
פסוק pasuk to be explicitly saying don't do it on שבת Shabbos
and therefore we're saying that this happened on שבת. Shabbos. Yes?
But it never says לא תוציא lo sotzi either, he says איש
ואישה אל יעשו עוד מלאכה. ish v'ishah al ya'asu od melachah.
I know, okay, so that's again this is how the גמרא Gemara
is reading it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Now once we're talking that this is the אב, av, we're going
to ask somewhat of a general question which we could ask anywhere
and actually the גמרא Gemara does in other places ask it elsewhere.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. מכדי, Michdi, says the גמרא.
Gemara.
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I jumped ahead. First we ask the question
about the reverse. אשכחן הוצאה, Ashchan hotza'ah, so that's going from taking
out from private to public. הכנסה מנא לן? Hachnasah m'na lan? How
about the reverse? Bringing in from רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim to רשות
היחיד? reshus ha-yachid? So here it actually says that no, that we
can at least do by ourselves. סברא, Svara, that we can say
by logic. מכדי, Michdi, let's see, מרשות לרשות, me-reshus l'reshus, it's going
from one domain to another. מה לי אפוקי מה לי עיולי? mah
li apukei mah li iyulei? What difference does it make if you
go out or go in? Of course in other places by carrying
we don't, well, okay, in other places by carrying we don't abstract.
So it's a little unclear why here we feel we can, but
the גמרא Gemara is saying this we assume is essentially the same.
Okay. מיהו הוצאה אב, Mihu hotza'ah av, but we still call הוצאה
hotza'ah the אב, av, and הכנסה, hachnasah, which isn't explicit, תולדה, toladah,
that is a תולדה, toladah, that's a derivative.
ומכדי, U'michdi, the גמרא Gemara says, אהא מחייב ואהא מחייב. aha mechayav
v'aha mechayav. You transgress whether it's the אב av or the תולדה.
toladah. אמאי קרי להאי אב ואמאי קרי להאי תולדה? Amai kari l'hai
av v'amai kari l'hai toladah? So why do you call one of
them אב av and
why do you
call one of them תולדה? toladah? What is the purpose, what's the
difference between an אב Av and a תולדה? Tolada? An אב Av
was in the משכן Mishkan explicit, a תולדה Tolada was not. What's
the purpose of giving them different labels if they're all אסור? Asur?
So here's the difference purpose of giving them different labels. נפקא מינה,
Nafka mina, the difference is, עביד שתי אבות בהדי הדדי, avid shtei
avot bahadi hadadi, if you do two אבות, Avot, different אבות, Avot,
like planting and cutting at the same time in one state of
forgetfulness, אי נמי שתי תולדות בהדי הדדי i nami shtei toldot bahadi
hadadi or two תולדות toldot of different אבות, Avot, right, at the
same time, מחייב תרתי, mechayev tarti, you're חייב chayav two separate חטאות.
chataot. דאי עביד אב ותולדה דידיה, d'ee avid av v'tolada dideih, but
if you do an אב Av and its תולדה, Tolada, so לא
מחייב אלא חדא, lo mechayev ela chada, you only bring one sin
offering. So what's the purpose of grouping them as אב Av and
תולדה? Tolada? Why don't you just give a full list of every
single act that's חייב? chayav? No, we group them as אב Av
and תולדה Tolada to say if you do a lot of things
in the same group in the same state of forgetfulness, you only
bring one קרבן. korban. It's like we're relearning the basics here, okay?
Now, ולרבי אליעזר דמחייב אתולדה במקום אב, U'l'Rabbi Eliezer d'mechayev a'tolada b'makom
av, how about רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
even if you do a תולדה toldah and the אב Av at
the same state, you bring two קרבנות. korbanot. So if that's true,
what's the point of creating these groups? אמאי קרו ליה אב ואמאי
קרו ליה תולדה? Amai karu lei av v'amai karu lei tolada? Why
is one called an אב Av and one called a תולדה? Tolada?
By the way, I should say something about רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
ties into something you learned two days ago, because remember you also
learned two days ago right רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was the one
that said you're חייב chayav for milking and for making cheese, and
the גמרא Gemara didn't exactly understand why. It said חולב משום מאי
מחייב משום חולב, מגבן משום מאי מחייב משום מגבן, Cholev mishum mai
mechayev mishum cholev, megaven mishum mai mechayev mishum megaven, right? So maybe
that's because רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer doesn't really fundamentally buy into this
whole אב תולדה av tolda principle. And if he has a much
flatter understanding of like no, there's a lot of things that are
אסור, asur, maybe not thirty-nine, we're just going to list you all
these different things that are אסור. asur. So חולב Cholev could be
חייב chayav משום חולב, mishum cholev, okay? You don't have to do
this type of grouping. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer seems to have a
different type of an approach to thinking of מלאכות melakhot on שבת.
Shabbat. But now the גמרא Gemara says, so according to him, do
we like—it assumes we at least do have these labels. What's the
point of these labels? If you're חייב chayav on an אב Av
and a תולדה, Tolada, you're חייב chayav each one, you know, you're
חייב chayav two קרבנות korbanot and not one. So ולרבי אליעזר דמחייב
אתולדה במקום אב אמאי קרו ליה אב ואמאי קרו ליה תולדה? U'l'Rabbi
Eliezer d'mechayev a'tolada b'makom av amai karu lei av v'amai karu lei
tolada? What's the point? הך דהוה במשכן חשיבא קרי ליה אב. Hach
d'hava b'Mishkan chashiva kari lei av. The ones that were in the
משכן Mishkan are important, those are called an אב. Av. הך דלא
הוה במשכן חשיבא לא קרי ליה אב. Hach d'la hava b'Mishkan chashiva
lo kari lei av. Those that weren't important in the
משכן Mishkan they don't call an אב, Av, they call a תולדה.
Tolada. Meaning you're right, it's there is no halakhic difference, there's no
halakhic point of giving it that label, it's only a way of
labeling these were the ones that were in the משכן, Mishkan, these
were not in the משכן. Mishkan. But at the end of the
day, it doesn't really matter what label you have, he doesn't really
have this אב תולדה Av Tolda grouping, it really is all arbitrary.
Okay, not arbitrary, but whatever, it's just about labels, it's not about
any halakhic difference. Now, תוספות Tosafot has a couple of quest—how to
read—has a question of how to read this. הך דהוה במשכן, Hach
d'hava b'Mishkan, do you read it those that were in the משכן
Mishkan by definition are the חשיבא, chashiva, are the important ones and
therefore they're an אב Av and those that weren't are not important,
okay, and therefore they're a תולדה? Tolada? Or do you read it
that you need two criteria to be an אב? Av? What were
the two criteria you would need to be an אב? Av?
הוה במשכן וחשיבא.
Hava b'Mishkan v'chashiva. You have to be—הוה במשכן וחשיבא.
hava b'Mishkan
v'chashiva.
Some have that גרסא. girsa. Okay, so is it that not everything
in the משכן Mishkan gets to be called an אב? Av? If
it's in the משכן Mishkan and important, you get to be called
an אב. Av. If it's not in the משכן Mishkan or if
it wasn't important, then you're going to be a תולדה. Tolada. So
that's an interesting question about—I know, so the rabbis—so that's an interesting
question about how to label the אב. Av. But what have we
said now? We have said that an אב Av is the things
that let's say were in the משכן Mishkan and either by definition
important, plus important, okay, either one or two criteria, what you derive
from them is a תולדה. Tolada. What is the point of having
those types of groupings rather than straight lists? The point of having
that grouping is everything in the אב תולדה Av Tolda category is
one קרבן. korban. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says no, it's multiple קרבנות.
korbanot. So is what's the point of the grouping? So the גמרא
Gemara reacts you know, yeah, according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer there's
no point of the grouping, these are just labels of identifying where
we learn them from, but there really is fundamentally none of this
אב תולדה Av Tolda grouping according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Okay,
תוספות Tosafot suggests that even according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer there
would be a significance and this he says is maybe what the
גמרא Gemara means about if you gave somebody התראה. hatra'ah. Like if
I said don't water your plants, you're חייב משום זורע, chayav mishum
zoreiah, right, even though you're not being זורע zoreiah when you water
your plants, but it derives from זורע. zoreiah. So then according to
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer maybe the grouping is still important that you
can give התראה, hatra'ah, you can give warning for the אב Av
category even when you're doing a תולדה. Tolada. But the גמרא Gemara
doesn't say that. And again I would say that it suggests Rabbi
Eliezer has a different way of thinking מלאכות שבת melachot Shabbat without
these fundamental thirty-nine groupings, and that I think explains to some degree
the גמרא Gemara earlier where he had a broader sense of what's
חייב chayav than the רבנן, Rabanan, right? And by the way I
should say right we saw that twice. We saw that about milking
and you saw that in the משנה Mishnah about putting on the
makeup and about braiding the hair, right? So if you don't start
by a thirty-nine אבות avot and I have to fit it into
an אב av category and if I don't it's a שבות, shvut,
that's what the רבנן Rabanan did and that's why they said braiding
the hair and the makeup was a was a דרבנן. derabanan. But
if you don't have a fundamental אב av תולדה toldah category, you
can have a very different criteria for defining what a מלאכה melachah
is. And it really seems like that is Rabbi Eliezer's approach.
Yeah, so there's two parts to what you just said. Let's say
I say don't don't bake because of משום אופה. mishum ofeh. Yes.
Is that then an אב? av?
Yes,
well you don't get killed because you well, תוספות Tosafot says,
the גמרא Gemara is clear you need to give the right התראה.
hatra'ah.
But then the other question is though, but we we took great
pains to, you know, make sure that this is exactly the way
they did it in the משכן. Mishkan. Right. But then, but then,
I mean we're going to talk about it later, you know, but
the גמרא Gemara goes it doesn't seem to like, you know, now
we're We're getting there!
That's the whole point of having this conversation. So let's keep on
going.
So is he supposed to not hold of the thirty-nine מלאכות melachot
at all? What? Does Rabbi Eliezer not hold of the thirty-nine מלאכות?
melachot?
Well, if he doesn't have fundamentally the categories, I mean he doesn't
deny that those things are מלאכות, melachot, but if he fundamentally doesn't
categorize them...
That's the question.
I mean the גמרא Gemara says it's all just a naming issue.
Thirty-nine מלאכות melachot were thirty-nine things that were in the משכן. Mishkan.
But fundamentally there's a lot of other things which we call תולדות,
toldot, okay, and
and those have are distinct and if you do a תולדה toldah
and an אב av you bring two קרבנות. korbanot. Now, we would
before I said what I did, I'm not the first person to
say it, you would have thought that he still understands that a
תולדה toldah is derived from an אב, av, that ultimately you have
to be based on an אב, av, right? As opposed to just
saying no, like things we will figure it out on our own.
Okay, so the status the status might be the same, but is
it derived from the אב? av? What I was suggesting, and again
I'm not the only one who says, you know I've heard some
academics that make that point, that it seems like he doesn't need
to fit them into categories, you know? And if you remember the
רב יוסף Rav Yosef said that not everybody learned thirty-nine מלאכות melachot
from the משכן. Mishkan. One way of understanding thirty-nine מלאכות melachot was
just חזל Chazal looked out in the world and they saw what
was important types of activities and they they figured it out. So
if that's true, you don't have to derive it from a specific
set of thirty-nine. Okay, so that's certainly a way of thinking about
Rabbi Eliezer. Okay, let's continue now in the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא
Gemara says like this: אי נמי I nami says the גמרא, Gemara,
where are we? אי נמי הכא כתיבא קרי ליה אב והכא דלא
כתיבא קרי ליה תולדה. I nami hacha ketiva kari lei av vehacha
d'lo ketiva kari lei toldah. If it's written it's an אב av
and if it's not it's a תולדה. toldah. So תוספות Tosafot says
you only need the idea of written as opposed to משכן Mishkan
for which מלאכה? melachah? הוצאה. hotza'ah.
Carrying, right? Carrying is the one מלאכה melachah that had to be
written. That's how we started the conversation. I couldn't have figured it
out by myself because it's not it's not a creative labor. So
what defines אב av versus תולדה? toldah? Either it was in the
משכן, Mishkan, I'll figure it out myself, or it's written, which is
carrying. And things that weren't in the משכן Mishkan or weren't written,
those are a תולדה. toldah. So within the carrying context, going from
רשות היחיד reshut hayachid to רשות הרבים reshut harabim is written—I'm sorry,
רשות הרבים reshut harabim to—no, I'm sorry, רשות היחיד reshut hayachid to
רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, bringing to מחנה לויה machaneh leviyah is written.
That's an אב. av. Going the other way, which I figured out
myself, that's a תולדה toldah because it wasn't written. Okay, so now
we know now we know הוצאה hotza'ah and הכנסה. hachnasah. Now it
continues. והדתנן, Veha detnan, that which we taught in a משנה Mishnah
coming up: הזורק ארבע אמות בכותל למעלה מעשרה טפחים כזורק באוויר. Hazorek
arba amot bekotel lemalah me'asarah tefachim kezorek ba'avir. If you threw four
אמות amot in the public domain but it was higher than ten
טפחים tefachim and it hit a wall and stuck on the wall,
then you're פטור patur because it was above the airspace, it's like
throwing in the air. למטה מעשרה טפחים, Lematah me'asarah tefachim, if it
was under ten טפחים, tefachim, כזורק בארץ, kezorek ba'aretz, it's like you
threw on the ground and therefore it's like you threw in the
רשות הרבים reshut harabim and if it hit the wall and sticks
on it, then it came to rest, then you're חייב. chayav. והזורק
בארץ ארבע אמות, Vehazorek ba'aretz arba amot, and if you threw four
אמות amot and it was on the ground, then חייב, chayav, you're
חייב. chayav. So now the גמרא Gemara says, so the reason we're
quoting this is to introduce the principle which is similar to the
beginning of our משנה, Mishnah, that you're חייב chayav not only for
carrying but even for throwing. So the
גמרא Gemara says: זורק ארבע אמות ברשות הרבים מנלן דמיחייב? Zorek arba
amot b'reshut harabim minalan demichayev? How do you know that throwing four
אמות amot in רשות הרבים reshut harabim is חייב? chayav? You could
have also asked how do you know that throwing from a private
to a public domain is חייב? chayav? Okay, we got carrying from
private to public. We at least were able to abstract without it
being written the reverse. But now again we're working with this general
sense that everything has to be written about carrying. We have a
very limited range of what we can abstract. So the גמרא Gemara
says how do you know about throwing? But actually before the גמרא
Gemara is asking about throwing, it's also asking about throwing where where
are you throwing here? From private to public or public to private?
Now what's the case? ארבע אמות Arba Amot in רשות הרבים, Reshut
Harabbim, right? So that's a whole other category. We got the category
of private public רשות היחיד Reshut Hayachid רשות הרבים, Reshut Harabbim, but
a whole other category of carrying is ארבע אמות Arba Amot in
רשות הרבים. Reshut Harabbim. Where does that come from? Okay. So, let's
figure that out. Where does this ארבע אמות Arba Amot come and
where does it come in terms of throwing?
Is it literal about throwing? Is it mean bowling also or? I
don't know.
Let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay. אמר רב
יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, שכן אורגי יריעות זורקין מחטיהן זה לזה. sheken
orgei yeriyot zorkin machten ze la-ze. Again,
we're just imagining that this is what happened when you are weaving
your the curtains, they would throw needles, the sewing needles one to
another. Okay, and assuming presumably that would be in a רשות הרבים.
Reshut Harabbim. Says גמרא Gemara says, אורגין, Orgin, wait, weavers? מחטין למה
להו? Machten lama lehu? What are they doing with needles, right? Needles
are for sewing, not for weaving. Weaving is making the cloth. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אלא שכן תופרי יריעות זורקין מחטיהן זה לזה.
ella sheken tofrei yeriyot zorkin machten ze la-ze. Fine. Those that were
sewing the curtains would throw needles one to another. Yay, could you
lend me your needle, lend me your thread, you'd throw it and
you would throw it ארבע אמות, Arba Amot, right, right, whatever, like
don't run with scissors. Anyway, ארבע אמות Arba Amot in רשות הרבים.
Reshut Harabbim. So the גמרא Gemara says, ודילמא גבי הדדי הוי יתבי?
ve-dilma gabei hadadi havi yasvei?
Maybe I was you know they were sitting next to one another.
You didn't have to throw it, you could hand it and it
wasn't ארבע אמות. Arba Amot. So the גמרא Gemara says no, מתו
הדדי במחטא, mathu hadadi be-machta, if you're
if you're sewing you don't want the guy sitting right next to
you, you'll poke him with your with your you know needle. So
the גמרא Gemara says, alright, not right next to. ודילמא בתוך ארבע
אמות הוי יתבי? ve-dilma be-tokh arba amot havi yasvei? So you were
two feet away, you were three feet away, but still maybe it
was within ארבע אמות. Arba Amot. How do you know it was
ארבע אמות Arba Amot away? אלא אמר רב חסדא, ella amar Rav
Hisda, fine, forget about the sewing, let's go back to the weaving.
שכן אורגי יריעות זורקין בוכייר ביריעה. sheken orgei yeriyot zorkin bokhayer be-yeria.
How do you weave? How do you weave is you take a
shuttle, right? You know the whole weaving thing, I mean we haven't
really discussed this yet in depth but basically you know weaving has
one thread going over and under, over and under. So some brilliant
person figured out that the way to do it is you have
the threads alternating on two different frames and you lift up the
frame, you throw it one way, then you then you reverse and
you lift up the other frame and you throw it the other
way and it effectively does the under and over. So how would
they throw it across? They'd throw it across with with a shuttle.
Basically they'd wrap it around some type of a you know spool
and throw it and then it would you know go through and
then they would reverse the things and throw it the other way.
So when they're weaving the normal part of weaving is throwing the
shuttle and that you would throw if you had a big if
you had a big cloth that would be ארבע אמות. Arba Amot.
ובהא ב רשות הרבים? ve-ha be-Reshut Harabbim?
Presumably you're doing this in the רשות הרבים, Reshut Harabbim, right? Which
is also a question that could be asked. So the גמרא Gemara
says, והא איהו אוגדו בידו. ve-ha ihu ogdo be-yado. One minute says
the גמרא, Gemara, if the if you're throwing the shuttle the string
remains on your side of the of the of the fabric. So
you haven't fully taken the shuttle out. Remember we had the whole
thing of the basket, ninety percent out, a little bit in, you
haven't yet fully taken it a hundred percent out. So here part
of this object is still with you and therefore it's not חייב.
chayav. So the גמרא Gemara says, בניסכא בתרא, beniska batra, with the
last thread. The last thread on the shuttle when you throw it
back right, then it doesn't stay with you and you've carried the
shuttle, you've thrown the shuttle ארבע אמות. Arba Amot. So the גמרא
Gemara says, והא במקום פטור קאזלה? ve-ha be-makom patur ka-azla? But even
if you're standing in רשות הרבים, Reshut Harabbim, the shuttle is a
מקום פטור, makom patur, okay, because this area of the shuttle right,
nobody's walking through there. It's not a רשות הרבים, Reshut Harabbim, it's
not even a כרמלית karmelis because it's not ארבע אמות Arba Amot
by ארבע אמות. Arba Amot. Maybe it's long, wide but it's not
long in the other direction. So the גמרא Gemara says you know
you're not throwing it in a רשות הרבים. Reshut Harabbim. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אלא שכן אורגי יריעות זורקין בוכייר לשאליהן. ella sheken
orgei yeriyot zorkin bokhayer le-sha-aleha.
Similar to what we were saying before about the needle. The guy
next to me needs a shuttle, oh you want a shuttle? Here,
catch. So you'd throw your shuttle to the guy next to you
who needed a shuttle.
You're not going over your curtain?
Who knows. ודילמא ve-dilma the גמרא Gemara says, גבי הדדי הוי יתבי?
gabei hadadi havi yasvei?
Maybe he was sitting right next to you. How do you know
you threw it ארבע אמות? Arba Amot? So מתו הדדי בחיבא. mathu
hadadi be-khiba.
No, because you don't want the guy working the other guy working
to be right next to you. You'll hit another when you're you
know at the edge of the garment. So basically you don't want
to be standing right next to the guy who's working on something
else. So the גמרא Gemara says, ודילמא שחופי הוי משחפי? ve-dilma she-khufei
havi meshakhefi? Okay,
so you weren't standing directly behind, but maybe you're sort of like
alternating right? So the guy I don't want somebody else like right
behind me or right over here. But if he's a little bit
removed he can still be within ארבע אמות Arba Amot and I
won't bump into him. So again the question is how do you
know that they were ארבע אמות Arba Amot apart? ודילמא גבי הדדי
מתו הדדי בעבידתייהו ותו ve-dilma gabei hadadi mathu hadadi be-avudatayehu ve-tu
and in addition, מי שיילי מהדדי? mi shayli me-hadadi? Since when did
people have to borrow their friends' you know stuff in the משכן?
Mishkan? דתניא לודא, de-tanya luda, we talked לודא luda taught, איש איש
ממלאכתו אשר הם עושים. ish ish mi-melakhto asher hem osim.
Every person from their work which they were doing. ממלאכתו הוא עושה,
mi-melakhto hu oseh, ממלאכתו הוא עושה ואינו עושה ממלאכת חבירו. mi-melakhto hu
oseh ve-eino oseh mi-melakhat havero. Every person did their own work. You
didn't need to borrow anything from your friend. You didn't need your
friend's help. Everybody was fully self-sufficient when they were doing the משכן.
Mishkan.
And also they had so much stuff. ותו *V'tu*, alright, ותו *V'tu*,
and anyway says גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, forget that, forget throwing. מעביר ארבע
אמות ברשות הרבים מנלן דמיחייב *Ma'avir arba amos birshus harabim minalan demichayev*?
How do you know carrying four אמות *amos* in רשות הרבים *reshus
harabim* is מנלן דמיחייב *minalan demichayev*? אלא כל ארבע אמות ברשות הרבים
גמרא גמירא לה *Ela kol arba amos birshus harabim gemara gemira lah*.
Fine, that we know by tradition. Okay, again, not that we can
do it by ourselves, the abstracting we can't do it. Anyway, how
do you abstract from רשות היחיד *reshus hayachid* to רשות הרבים *reshus
harabim* to four אמות *amos* in רשות הרבים *reshus harabim*? So according
to this גמרא *Gemara*, here's what we know by carrying. Carrying from
a house to a רשות הרבים *reshus harabim*, that's in the פסוק
*pasuk*. That's what we say is in the פסוק *pasuk*. The reverse,
that we're able to abstract. Four אמות *amos* in רשות הרבים *reshus
harabim*, whether carrying or throwing, that's all just tradition. Again, because we
have a limited amount we can do with carrying, we can't abstract
like we can by other things. So the one thing that we
haven't really told us how we know, is how do we know
throwing from a private to a public domain, right? How do we
know throwing is included in carrying? That's how our גמרא *Gemara* starts.
And
the first line in the גמרא *Gemara* is מכדי זריקה תולדה דהוצאה
היא *Michdi zerika toldah dehotza'ah hi*. It's a תולדה *toldah* of הוצאה
*hotza'ah*. But how do we know? So presumably we have to say
that we were able to abstract that as well. So some minimal
aspects we're able to abstract: going רשות היחיד *reshus hayachid* to רשות
הרבים *reshus harabim*, doing the reverse, זריקה *zerika* as opposed to carrying.
Other things though needed to be explicitly written or specifically taught as
a tradition, like the four אמות *amos* in רשות הרבים *reshus harabim*.
הלכתא למשה מסיני *Halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai*?
Yes, presumably הלכתא למשה מסיני *halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai*.
Let's just read a little more in the גמרא *Gemara* before we
have two minutes left. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל *Amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel*: מקושש mekoshesh *Mekoshesh*, now that we're talking about carrying and
we're trying to find a basis for it in the תורה *Torah*,
let's talk about the מקושש mekoshesh. *mekoshesh*, the one who collected the
wood, who was the case of being put to death for חילול
שבת *chilul Shabbos*. So what was his עבירה *aveira*? So the גמרא
*Gemara* says, so רב יהודה אמר שמואל *Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel* says:
מעביר ארבע אמות ברשות הרבים הוה *Ma'avir arba amos birshus harabim havah*.
He carried four אמות *amos* in רשות הרבים *reshus harabim*. So that's
great. That gives you an example in the תורה *Torah*. You don't
have to just say it's a tradition. No, implicit in this story
was the problem was carrying four אמות *amos*. Of course, the tradition
still has to tell you that that's what the story was about,
but okay. במתניתא תנא *B'masnisa tana*, in a ברייתא *braisa* we taught:
תולש הוה *Tolesh havah*. No, his problem was that he pulled out
wood that was growing from a tree. תולש *Tolesh*, that was his
עבירה *aveira*. רב אחא בר יעקב אמר מעמר הוה *Rav Achah bar
Yaakov amar ma'amer havah*, which seems to make the most sense. He
gathered, gathering things that fell off of a tree. He gathered up
the branches. מעמר *Ma'amer*, and that's a מלאכה *melacha*. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says: למאי נפקא מינה *L'mai nafka mina*? Who cares? It's all
just an historical question. What practical difference does it make what his
עבירה *aveira* was? לכדרב *L'chidarav*, to teach you what רב *Rav* says.
This really shows you how the גמרא *Gemara* is not interested in
history for its own sake. דאמר רב *D'amar רב*: רב *Rav* said:
מצאתי מגילת סתרים *Matzasi megillas sesarim*. I found a hidden scroll. רש״י
*Rashi* says it would be the sense about hidden, says רש״י *Rashi*,
is because they generally wouldn't write down הלכות *halachos*, but this they
did write down so they couldn't publicize it. So I found a
hidden scroll בי רב חייא *bei Rav Chiyya*, in the house of
רב חייא *Rav Chiyya*. דכתיב בה *Dichsiv bah*, it was written the
following thing: איסי בן יהודה Isi Ben Yehuda. אומר *Isi ben Yehuda
omer*. איסי בן יהודה *Isi ben Yehuda* says: אבות מלאכות ארבעים חסר
אחת *Avos melachos arbaim chaser achas*. There are 39 מלאכות *melachos*. ואינו
חייב אלא אחת *v'eino chayav ela achas*. And you're only חייב *chayav*
one. What does it mean one? אחת ותו לא *Achas vesu lo*?
You're only חייב *chayav* on one? והתנן אבות מלאכות ארבעים חסר אחת
*Vehatnan avos melachos arbaim chaser achas*. There are 39 מלאכות *melachos*. והוינן
במניינא למה לי *V'havinan bemanyana lama li*? Why do you have to
say explicitly 39? I can count. ואמר רבי יוחנן שאם עשאן כולם
בהעלם אחד חייב על כל אחת ואחת *Ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan she'im asan
kulam be'he'elem echad chayav al kol achas ve'achas*. To tell you you
can bring 39 חטאות *chata'os* if you do all of the מלאכות
*melachos* and forget about all of them, you can bring up to
39 מלאכות *melachos*. So how could anybody say you only bring one,
meaning I guess we didn't assume that he could argue that radically
on רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, that you only bring one sin offering.
So אימא *Eima*, so don't have it say you can only bring
one sin offering, but say: אינו חייב על אחת מהן *eino chayav
al achas mehen*. One of the 39 מלאכות *melachos* you're not חייב
*chayav* on. Maybe it's biblically forbidden, but you don't bring a sin
offering and you're not חייב מיתה chayav misa *chayav misa*. It's not
as weighty as the rest. Now you understand why it was a
hidden scroll. That's a very dangerous idea. One of the 39 מלאכות
*melachos* you're not חייב מיתה chayav misa. *chayav misa*. So which one
is it? We don't know. So רב יהודה פשיטא ליה *Rav Yehuda
pshita leh*, so for רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* who said that the
מקושש *mekoshesh*
was carrying, for him it's obvious דהמעביר חייב *de'hama'avir chayav*, that carrying
is not that one. That carrying is definitely חייב *chayav*, it's not
the one of the 39 that איסי בן יהודה *Isi ben Yehuda*
says it's not חייב מיתה *chayav misa*. ומתניתא פשיטא ליה *U'masnisa pshita
leh*, the ברייתא *braisa* that says that what he did was he
uprooted something that was growing, דתולש חייב *detolesh chayav*. It's obvious that
תולש *tolesh* is certainly not the one that you would be exempt
for, that you would not be חייב מיתה *chayav misa*. ולרב אחא
בר יעקב פשיטא ליה *U'leRav Achah bar Yaakov pshita leh*, and for
רב אחא בר יעקב *Rav Achah bar Yaakov* it's obvious to him
דמעמר חייב *dem'amer chayav*. That מעמר *ma'amer* is the—is definitely חייב *chayav*
and is not one of the ones that might not be. מר
סבר הא מילתא לא מספקא ליה *Mar savar ha milta lo mesapka
leh*. One says this at least was not under doubt. ומר סבר
הא מילתא לא מספקא ליה *Umar savar ha milta lo mesapka leh*.
And the other says his was at least not under doubt. But
by the way, this is an important thing to be bringing up
here, because after just having said about how carrying is such a
different type of a מלאכה *melacha*, if somebody told you... one of
the מלאכות you're not חייב מיתה for, guess which one? I think
we all would have assumed that carrying would have been that. It
seems to be the most, the most different of all of them
as we've been saying. But here the גמרא ends by saying that
at least according to those that understand the מקושש was carrying, it
is not the one. And this is only of course according to
איסי בן יהודה. It's not how we rule. We rule that every
single one of the thirty-nine is חייב מיתה. We will continue tomorrow
with the story of מקושש.